So, where are the robots?
إذا، أين الآليين؟
We've been told for 40 years already that they're coming soon.
مذ 40 عام وهم يقولون أنهم قادمون قريبا
Very soon they'll be doing everything for us.
قريبا سيقومون بجميع الأعمال
They'll be cooking, cleaning, buying things, shopping, building. But they aren't here.
سيطهون، ينظفون، يشترون، يتسوقون، ويبنون. إلا أنهم ليسو هنا
Meanwhile, we have illegal immigrants doing all the work,
بينما، لدينا مهاجرين غير شرعيين يقومون بكل العمل
but we don't have any robots.
ولكن لا يوجد أس آليين
So what can we do about that? What can we say?
فماذا يمكننا فعله بهذا الخصوص؟ ماذا نقول؟
So I want to give a little bit of a different perspective
أود أن أعطي وجهة نظر مختلفة
of how we can perhaps look at these things in a little bit of a different way.
عن كيف يمكننا النظر إلى هذه الأمور بطريقة مختلفة بعض الشيء
And this is an x-ray picture
وهذه أشعة سينية
of a real beetle, and a Swiss watch, back from '88. You look at that --
لخنفساء حقيقية، وساعة سويسرية، منذ عام 88. انظروا إلى ذلك
what was true then is certainly true today.
ما كان حقيقة حينها لا يزال بكل تأكيد حقيقيا اليوم
We can still make the pieces. We can make the right pieces.
لازلنا قادرين على صنع الأجزاء، يمكننا صنع الأجزاء الصحيحة
We can make the circuitry of the right computational power,
يمكننا صنع الدوائر ذات القدرة الحسابية الصحيحة
but we can't actually put them together to make something
ولكننا لا نستطيع جمعها لصنع شيء
that will actually work and be as adaptive as these systems.
سيعمل في الواقع ويكون قادر على التلاؤم مثل هذه الأنظمة
So let's try to look at it from a different perspective.
لذا دعونا نحاول النظر إلى الموضوع من زاوية أخرى
Let's summon the best designer, the mother of all designers.
لنستدعي أفضل المصممين، كبير المصممين:
Let's see what evolution can do for us.
دعنى نرى ما يمكن للتطور فعله لنا
So we threw in -- we created a primordial soup
فنرمي -- نصنع شربة بدائية
with lots of pieces of robots -- with bars, with motors, with neurons.
بها أجزاء كثيرة من الآليين: قضبان، محركات، أعصاب
Put them all together, and put all this under kind of natural selection,
نضعهم جميعا، ونضعها جميعا ضمن الانتقاء الطبيعي
under mutation, and rewarded things for how well they can move forward.
مع التحورات، ونكافئ الأشياء على مدى قدرتها على التحرك للامام
A very simple task, and it's interesting to see what kind of things came out of that.
مهمة سهلة جدا، ومن المثير أن نرى ما هي النتائج من ذلك
So if you look, you can see a lot of different machines
إذا نظرتم، يمكنكم رؤية مجموعة من الآلات المختلفة
come out of this. They all move around.
تنتج من ذلك. كلها تتحرك
They all crawl in different ways, and you can see on the right,
كلها تزحف يطرق مختلفة، وعلى اليمين يمكنكم رؤية
that we actually made a couple of these things,
أننا صنعنا فعليا بعض هذه الأشياء
and they work in reality. These are not very fantastic robots,
وهي تعمل في الواقع. هؤلاء ليسو آليين مثاليين
but they evolved to do exactly what we reward them for:
ولكنهم تتطوروا لما أردناه منهم تماما
for moving forward. So that was all done in simulation,
التحرك للأمام. وكل هذا حدث في المحاكاة
but we can also do that on a real machine.
ولكننا نستطيع فعل ذلك على آلات حقيقية
Here's a physical robot that we actually
هذا آلي حقيقي قمنا في الواقع
have a population of brains,
لديه عدة أدمغة
competing, or evolving on the machine.
تتنافس أو تتطور على الآلة
It's like a rodeo show. They all get a ride on the machine,
إنه كمسابقة: كلهم ينتقلون على الآلة
and they get rewarded for how fast or how far
ويكافئون على المسافة أو السرعة
they can make the machine move forward.
التي ينقبون بها الآلة قدما
And you can see these robots are not ready
ويمكنكم رؤية أن هؤلاء الآليين ليسوا مستعدين
to take over the world yet, but
للسيطرة على العالم بعد، إلا
they gradually learn how to move forward,
أنهم يتعلمون تدريجيا كيف يتحركون للأمام
and they do this autonomously.
ويقومون بذلك وحدهم
So in these two examples, we had basically
في هذين المثالين، كانت لدينا مبدئيا
machines that learned how to walk in simulation,
آلات تعلمت كيف تتحرك في المحاكاة
and also machines that learned how to walk in reality.
وآلات تعلمت كيف تمشي في الحقيقة
But I want to show you a different approach,
ولكنني أريد أن أطلعكم على منهجية مختلفة
and this is this robot over here, which has four legs.
وهي هذا الآلي، هنا، ولديه أربعة أرجل
It has eight motors, four on the knees and four on the hip.
ثماني محركات، أربع على الركب وأربع على الفخذ
It has also two tilt sensors that tell the machine
ولديه حساسان للميلان ليخبران الآلة
which way it's tilting.
في أي اتجاه تميل
But this machine doesn't know what it looks like.
ولكن هذه الآلة لا تعرف كيف تبدو
You look at it and you see it has four legs,
تنظرون إليها وترون أن لها أربعة أرجل
the machine doesn't know if it's a snake, if it's a tree,
الآلة لا تعرف ما إذا كانت ثعبان، أو شجرة
it doesn't have any idea what it looks like,
ليست لديها أدنى فكرة عن شكلها
but it's going to try to find that out.
ولكنها ستحاول أن تكتشف
Initially, it does some random motion,
بدايتا، تقوم ببعض الحركات العشوائية
and then it tries to figure out what it might look like.
وتقوم بعد ذلك بمحاولة معرفة ما قد يكون شكلها
And you're seeing a lot of things passing through its minds,
وترون العديد من الأمور تخطر بعقلها
a lot of self-models that try to explain the relationship
الكثير من النماذج لمحاولة شرح العلاقة
between actuation and sensing. It then tries to do
بين الفعل والإحساس -- ومن ثم تحاول أن
a second action that creates the most disagreement
تقوم بفعل ثاني يولد أكبر قدر من الخلاف
among predictions of these alternative models,
بين توقعات هذه النماذج المحتملة
like a scientist in a lab. Then it does that
مثل العالم في المختبر. ثم تقوم بذلك
and tries to explain that, and prune out its self-models.
وتحاول شرحه، وتهذب النموذج
This is the last cycle, and you can see it's pretty much
هذه هي الدورة الأخيرة، ويمكنكم رؤية أنها تقريبا
figured out what its self looks like. And once it has a self-model,
علمت ما هو شكلها، وبمجرد أن تتعلم نموذجها
it can use that to derive a pattern of locomotion.
يمكنها استخدام ذلك لاستنتاج نمط للحركة
So what you're seeing here are a couple of machines --
فما ترونه هنا هو بضعة آلات
a pattern of locomotion.
ونمط للحركة
We were hoping that it wass going to have a kind of evil, spidery walk,
كنا نأمل أنها ستحصل على مشية عنكبوتيه شريرة
but instead it created this pretty lame way of moving forward.
ولكن عوضا عن ذلك، أنشئت هذه الطريقة العرجاء للحركة
But when you look at that, you have to remember
ولكن حين تنظرون إلى ذلك، يحب أن تتذكروا
that this machine did not do any physical trials on how to move forward,
أن هذه الآلة لم تقم بأي تجارب عملية عن كيفية التقدم
nor did it have a model of itself.
ولم تكن لديها أي نموذج لنفسها
It kind of figured out what it looks like, and how to move forward,
لقد استكشفت شكلها، وكيف تتحرك
and then actually tried that out.
وثم قامت بالتجربة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, we'll move forward to a different idea.
سنتقدم إلى فكرة أخرى
So that was what happened when we had a couple of --
ذلك ما حدث عندما كانت لدينا بضعة
that's what happened when you had a couple of -- OK, OK, OK --
ذلك ما حدث عندما كانت لدينا بضعة -- حسنا، حسنا، حسنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- they don't like each other. So
لا يحبون بعضهم
there's a different robot.
يوجد آلي مختلف
That's what happened when the robots actually
هذا ما يحدث حين نكافئ
are rewarded for doing something.
الآليين على عمل أمر ما
What happens if you don't reward them for anything, you just throw them in?
ماذا يحدث إذا لم نكافئهم على أي شيء، فقط نرميهم؟
So we have these cubes, like the diagram showed here.
لدينا هذا المكعب، كما يوضح الرسم هنا
The cube can swivel, or flip on its side,
المكعب يستطيع الدوران أو التدحرج على جنبه
and we just throw 1,000 of these cubes into a soup --
ورمينا 1000 من هذه المكعبات في سائل
this is in simulation --and don't reward them for anything,
هذا في المحاكاة -- ولم نكافيءهم على أي شيء
we just let them flip. We pump energy into this
فقط تركناهم يتقلبون
and see what happens in a couple of mutations.
انظروا إلى ما يحدث بعد بضع تحورات
So, initially nothing happens, they're just flipping around there.
بدايتا، لا يحدث أي شيء، إنهم يتقلبون فحسب
But after a very short while, you can see these blue things
ولكن بعد فترة وجيزة، يمكنكم رؤية تلك الأشياء الزرقاء
on the right there begin to take over.
هناك على اليمين بدئت بالسيطرة
They begin to self-replicate. So in absence of any reward,
بدؤوا بالاستنساخ
the intrinsic reward is self-replication.
المكافئة الحقيقية هي الاستنساخ
And we've actually built a couple of these,
ولقد بنينا في الواقع القليل منها
and this is part of a larger robot made out of these cubes.
وهذا جزي من آلي أكبر مصنوع من هذه المكعبات
It's an accelerated view, where you can see the robot actually
هذه نظرة سريعة، حيث يمكنكم رؤية الآلي
carrying out some of its replication process.
يقوم فعليا بعملية الاستنساخ
So you're feeding it with more material -- cubes in this case --
فتزودها بالمواد -- المكعبات في هذه الحالة -ـ
and more energy, and it can make another robot.
والمزيد من الطاقة، ويمكنها صناعة آلي آخر
So of course, this is a very crude machine,
طبعا، هذه آلة بسيطة جدا
but we're working on a micro-scale version of these,
ولكننا نعمل على نسخة متناهية في الصغر منهم
and hopefully the cubes will be like a powder that you pour in.
ونأمل أن المكعبات ستصبح مثل البودرة وتقوم بسكبها
OK, so what can we learn? These robots are of course
حسنا، ماذا يمكننا أن نتعلم؟ هؤلاء الآليين بالطبع
not very useful in themselves, but they might teach us something
غير مفيدين بذاتهم، ولكن قد يعلمونا شيء
about how we can build better robots,
عن كيف يمكننا بناء آليين أفضل
and perhaps how humans, animals, create self-models and learn.
وربما كيف يقوم البشر، والحيوانات بتحديد نموذج الحركة والتعلم
And one of the things that I think is important
وأحد المواضيع المهمة في نظري
is that we have to get away from this idea
أننا يجب أن نبتعد عن فكرة
of designing the machines manually,
تصميم الآلات يدويا
but actually let them evolve and learn, like children,
ولكن أن ندعهم يتطورون ويتعلمون، كالأطفال
and perhaps that's the way we'll get there. Thank you.
وربما تلك هي الطريقة للوصول إلى هناك. شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)